Have you ever been totally stumped by the English present perfect tense?
英語の現在完了形に困ったことはありませんか？
You're not alone. It can feel like a real puzzle.
あなたは一人じゃありません。それは本当に難しいです。
Well, in this explainer, we are going to crack it once and for all.
この説明で、しっかり理解しましょう。
Okay, let's look at these two sentences.
まずはこの2つの文を見てみましょう。
On the surface, they seem almost identical, right?
表面上はほぼ同じに見えますよね？
I lost my bag, and I have lost my bag.
「私はバッグを失くした」と「私はバッグを失くしています」。
I mean, both are about losing a bag in the past.
どちらも過去にバッグを失くしたことについてです。
But that tiny little word, have, it changes everything.
でも、その小さな単語「have」が全てを変えます。
And it's all about what's happening right now.
現在の状況に関わるのです。
So let's solve this past and present puzzle.
では、この過去と現在のパズルを解きましょう。
By the time we're done here, you won't just understand the difference.
ここが終わる頃には、違いを理解できるだけでなく、
You'll feel confident using it. First things first, the basics.
自信を持って使えるようになります。まずは基本から。
The best way to think of the present perfect is like a bridge.
現在完了形は橋のように考えると良いです。
Its whole job, using have or has, plus a past participle,
「have」または「has」と過去分詞を使って、
is to connect something that happened in the past
過去に起こったことを
directly to the present moment.
現在に直接つなげるのが役割です。
So you see, it's not just about the past.
つまり、過去だけではないのです。
It's about how the past affects the now.
過去が現在にどう影響するかが重要です。
And this, right here, is the core idea you need to get.
これが理解すべき核心です。
The simple past, it talks about something
単純過去形は、
that is overdone, finished, the story's closed.
終わったこと、物語が閉じたことを語ります。
But the present perfect, that carries the result
しかし、現在完了形はその結果を
of that past action right into this very moment.
今この瞬間に持ち込むのです。
That's the secret sauce. All right, let's really break down
これがポイントです。では、違いを詳しく見てみましょう。
the difference that half makes.
「have」の影響を見てみましょう。
Seeing these examples side by side is what makes it all click.
これらの例を並べて見ることで、理解が深まります。
So, we're back to our original mystery.
さて、元の謎に戻りましょう。
I lost my bag versus I have lost my bag.
「私はバッグを失くした」と「私はバッグを失くしています」。
Let's put them under the microscope.
詳しく見てみましょう。
Okay, so if you say I lost my bag,
「私はバッグを失くした」と言うと、
you're just stating a historical fact.
ただの歴史的事実を述べているだけです。
The action of losing it is over. But what's the situation now?
失くした行為は終わっています。でも今の状況は？
We have no idea. Maybe you found it two minutes later.
全く分かりません。もしかしたら2分後に見つけたかもしれません。
The simple past leaves the present a complete mystery.
単純過去形では現在が完全に謎のままです。
But watch what happens when you add have.
でも、「have」を加えるとどうなるか見てみましょう。
I have lost my bag is all about the present result.
「私はバッグを失くしています」は現在の結果に関するものです。
It means the bag is gone and here's the key.
バッグはなく、ここが重要です。
It is still gone right now. You are standing there without your bag.
今もまだなく、あなたはバッグなしで立っています。
The result of that past action is still very much alive.
その過去の行為の結果は今も生きています。
Let's lock this concept in with another classic example.
この概念を別の例で確認しましょう。
What's the real difference between she went to America
「彼女はアメリカに行った」と
and she has gone to America? If you say she went to America,
「彼女はアメリカに行っています」の違いは何でしょう？
well, that's just a piece of her life story.
「彼女はアメリカに行った」と言うと、
She took a trip at some point. Was it last year, 10 years ago?
彼女の人生の一部を語っているだけです。
Is she back home now?
いつ行ったのか、昨年か10年前か？
Who knows, her current location is a total blank.
今は帰ってきているのか、誰にも分かりません。
But, if you say she has gone to America,
彼女の現在の場所は全く不明です。
the meaning becomes crystal clear.
しかし、「彼女はアメリカに行っています」と言うと、
It means she went and as a result of that trip, she is still there.
意味は明確になります。
She's not here. The consequence of her going is her current absence.
彼女は行った結果、今もそこにいるということです。
It's all about her status right now.
彼女はここにはいません。その結果が現在の不在です。
Okay, now that we've nailed the result aspect,
今の彼女の状況が全てです。
let's look at how we can get even more precise.
さて、結果の側面を理解したので、
We can use a few handy little adverbs
さらに正確に見てみましょう。
to talk about when something was completed.
完了した時期を話すために便利な副詞を使えます。
These three words, just, already, and yet,
「just」「already」「yet」の3つの言葉は、
are like best friends to the present perfect.
現在完了形の親友のようなものです。
Just means something happened a moment ago.
「just」は何かがつい最近起こったことを意味します。
Already tells us it happened sooner than we thought,
「already」は思ったより早く起こったことを示し、
and yet is what we use for questions and negatives,
「yet」は質問や否定文で使います。
kind of meaning up to this point.
ここまでの意味です。
And the grammar here is really simple.
文法はとてもシンプルです。
Just and already slide in perfectly right after have or has.
「just」と「already」は「have」や「has」の後に ぴったり入ります。
Yet, almost always hangs out at the very end of the sentence.
「yet」はほとんどいつも文の最後に来ます。
Super easy to remember. All right, time for a quick practice run.
覚えやすいですね。では、簡単な練習をしましょう。
How would you say this idea using the present perfect?
このアイデアを現在完了形でどう言いますか？
I finished my homework a moment ago. Exactly.
「さっき宿題を終えました。」その通りです。
I have just finished my homework.
「私はちょうど宿題を終えました。」
You see, the just pops in right after have
「just」は「have」のすぐ後に入って、 どれだけ最近かを強調します。分かりましたか？
and it emphasizes how recent it was. You got it?
次は、最も重要なルールです。
Now for probably the most important rule of them all.
これさえ覚えれば、よくある間違いを避けられます。
If you can remember this one thing,
これがゴールデンルールです。
you'll avoid a really common mistake.
現在完了形は「今」とのつながりが大事です。
Here it is. The golden rule. Because the present perfect is all about connecting to now,
過去の行動を固定する言葉とは使えません。 例えば、
you can never use it with words that lock an action in the past. I'm talking about words like
「yesterday」や「last week」、「2010年に」などです。
yesterday, last week, or in 2010. For instance, you just can't say,
「私は昨日鍵をなくしました」とは言えません。 「yesterday」はその出来事を
I have lost my key yesterday. The word yesterday acts like an anchor, pinning that event to a
過去の特定の時間に固定します。 現在とのつながりが切れてしまいます。
finished time. It breaks the bridge to the present. So you have to use the simple past.
だから、過去形を使わなければなりません。 「私は昨日鍵をなくしました。」
I lost my key yesterday." And it's the exact same idea here. Two years ago is a specific,
ここでも同じ考えです。「2年前」は特定の、 終了した時間のブロックです。
finished block of time. So you must say, she went to Italy two years ago. Never, she has gone.
だから、「彼女は2年前にイタリアに行きました」と言わなければなりません。 「彼女は行った」とは言えません。
So if you see a specific pastime marker, you know what to do. Simple past, every time.
特定の過去の時間を示す言葉があれば、 過去形を使うと分かります。
All right, let's wrap all this up and pack it into a simple toolkit that you can take with you.
では、これをまとめて、持ち運べる シンプルなツールキットにしましょう。
So here are the four big takeaways.
ここでの4つの大事なポイントです。
Number one, it's a bridge from the past to the present.
1つ目、過去から現在への橋です。
Two, it's all about the results that you feel right now.
2つ目、今感じている結果が重要です。
Three, you can use adverbs like just, already, and yet to add detail about completion.
3つ目、「just」「already」「yet」などの副詞を使って、 完了の詳細を加えられます。
And four, the big one, stay away from specific past-time words like yesterday.
4つ目、特に重要なこと、 「yesterday」のような特定の過去の言葉を避けることです。
So if you remember just one single thing today, let it be this.
もし今日1つだけ覚えることがあるなら、 これを覚えてください。
The present perfect is all about the now that is a result of the then.
現在完了形は、過去の結果としての「今」です。
It's always a story about consequences.
常に結果の物語です。
And that leaves us with one final intriguing question.
最後に興味深い質問があります。
We know she has gone to America means she's still there.
「彼女はアメリカに行った」というのは、 彼女がまだそこにいることを意味します。
But what if someone says she has been to America?
では、「彼女はアメリカに行ったことがある」と言ったら、 どういう意味になるのでしょうか？
What does that imply?
それは何を示唆しますか？
Well, that unlocks a whole different side of the present perfect, but that's a story
それは現在完了形の全く異なる側面を 解き放ちますが、それはまた別の話です。
for another time. Thanks for joining me.
ご参加ありがとうございました。